<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>breadiquette</title>
    <description>All things sourdough.
</description>
    <link>http://breadiquette.github.io</link>
    <atom:link href="http://breadiquette.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2020 17:16:07 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2020 17:16:07 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.7</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sourdough Cinnamon Toast Crunch</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am so excited about this recipe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a while now, I’ve been trying to find creative uses for my sourdough discard. I’ve done banana bread, crackers, granola, and so much more with it, but I’ve gotten tired of using the same recipes over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When doing my weekly grocery shopping recently, I thought I would briefly wander the aisles in search of something I could replicate with my sourdough starter. Most of the ideas I had weren’t too feasible (YOU try adding sourdough to minestrone soup), and some had already been done before. But when I turned down the cereal aisle, it struck me that I could use my discard to replicate a childhood favorite: cinnamon toast crunch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll concede- cinnamon toast crunch wasn’t my favorite sweet cereal as a kid, and we hardly ever ate it in my house, but it seemed like an easier project than fruit loops or lucky charms. Plus, I figured I could make it entirely from ingredients I already had in my pantry, so I wouldn’t have to purchase more ingredients just to use up my discard. The irony that the operative word of this cereal- toast- also happens to relate to sourdough isn’t lost on me either!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-process&quot;&gt;The Process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This recipe is incredibly straightforward. I modeled it after the recipes I’ve seen on the internet for sourdough crackers, following the general model of mix dough, refrigerate, roll out, bake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to keep oats as the basis of this cereal, so I first ground up some oats to make oat flour. In the finished product I use a combination of both oat flour and all purpose flour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used some homemade applesauce, which I made by cooking a peeled and chopped apple with some water and then pureeing the mixture. The applesauce binds the dough together, and it adds a subtle sweetness so you don’t have to add too much sugar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This recipe doesn’t have the most formal or complicated process, and I intend it that way. Throw the ingredients together and knead until you have a dough the consistency of pie dough. Then refrigerate for about a half an hour, roll it out, and bake it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/dough.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have a rolling pin, do you really think you can call yourself a baker??&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kidding. I don’t have a rolling pin, and most days I feel reasonably confident referring to myself as one. To roll out the dough, I simply flattened it into a disk, placed it between two sheets of parchment paper, and rolled it out with a glass bottle. You could also use a can of beans or a table leg if you’re really desperate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/kneading.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-results&quot;&gt;The Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, for how few ingredients this recipe has, I’m surprised at how similar it tastes to cinnamon toast crunch! I refrained from making the cereal super sweet, and I’m happy with the results. If you want your cereal to elicit a sugar high, however, feel free to increase the amount you use in the dough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only addendum I have for this recipe is that it doesn’t keep as long as boxed cereal, so it’s best made only for the day it’ll be consumed. The recipe is designed to serve two, or one very hungry person, but could easily be scaled up and down, especially if you’re willing to make slight modifications to the amount of applesauce needed to form the dough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, onto the recipe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 cup oats, ground into oat flour in a blender or food processor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1/3 cup sourdough starter discard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1/3 cup all purpose flour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1/4 tsp. salt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1/2 tsp. vanilla&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 tsp. cinnamon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 tbsp. + 1/4 cup sugar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;instructions&quot;&gt;Instructions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using your hands or a stand mixer, mix together the ingredients, reserving 2.5 tsp. cinnamon and 1/4 cup sugar for the topping. Once the mixture forms a dough similar to pie crust, form it into a ball and cover with plastic wrap. Refrigerate for thirty minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preheat the oven to 375 farenheit. Place the dough between two sheets of parchment paper and roll it as thin as possible, ideally only a few millimeters thick. In a small bowl, mix together the reserved cinnamon and sugar, and sprinkle it over both sides of the dough. Line a baking sheet with one of the sheets of parchment, and cut the dough into 1x1 cm squares. Bake on parchment for 9-12 minutes in preheated oven. Serve cereal with milk or enjoy it on its own!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/cinnacrunch.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/cerealpourblog.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://breadiquette.github.io/2020/09/26/Sourdough-Cinnamon-Toast-Crunch/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://breadiquette.github.io/2020/09/26/Sourdough-Cinnamon-Toast-Crunch/</guid>
        
        <category>Sourdough</category>
        
        <category>Bread</category>
        
        <category>Sweet</category>
        
        <category>Breakfast</category>
        
        <category>Vegan</category>
        
        <category>Oil Free</category>
        
        <category>Discard</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Gold Rush Sourdough</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Having surmounted the initial difficulties of making sourdough (getting my loaves to rise, timing, baking by feel rather than by measuring), I found myself faced with another set of challenges altogether: flavored breads and inclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m no stranger to the more “traditional” sourdough inclusions- I’ve made my fair share of jalepeño-cheddar batards and kalamata olive boules. In fact, one of my favorite loaves to date is a chocolate cherry loaf I made for a someone who is both a beloved friend and the creator of this blog!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But after experimenting with all sorts of sourdough inclusions, I wanted to make something truely unique. The internet has enough recipes for chocolate-cherry loaves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many of the best baking creations are devised, this loaf was dreamt up by the necessity to use up food in my pantry. I bought a head of ginger for cooking a few weeks ago, and found I couldn’t use it as quickly as I needed. While ruminating on this conundrum over my morning coffee, I decided to try making a sourdough with ginger. While I was at it, I though, I might as well candy the ginger, as I wasn’t sure a forty-odd minute sint in the oven would cut its spiciness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cinnamon, of course, would complement the ginger perfectly, as would cocoa powder. And, of course, the leftover coffee I’d just brewed would amplify the chocolatey cocoa powder flavor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, in a bout of creativity (subconciously inspired, of course, by the “flavors of fall” I see touted by my local Starbucks), Gold Rush Sourdough was born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-process&quot;&gt;The Process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The night before starting the bread, I pulled my starter out of the fridge and fed it. I’ve developed an incredibly precise method for its feeding, whereby I dump unspecified amounts of flour and water into its jar until it feels right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Starter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also candied the ginger. This didn’t take much effort, either. I peeled and chopped the ginger, then boiled it until it was nearly soft, which took about 35 minutes. Then, I removed most of the cooking liquid and added what looked to be an equal mass of sugar to the ginger. I continued to cook the ginger until it was coated with sugar and nearly dried out, whisking continuously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next morning, I autolyzed flour and water, as per usual, this time using a rather arbitrary ratio of about 85% bread flour to 15% whole wheat flour. After about an hour of autolyse, I added a generous quantity of starter, as well as cocoa powder and a few shakes of cinnamon. A half hour later, I worked in some salt, as well as the stale coffee from the day before, which I warmed slightly and sugared liberally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, the dough smelled incredible! Around the third stretch and fold (I performed four in total), I worked in the candied ginger. I continued the bulk proof for a mere two more hours, because my radiators inexplicably kicked on and made my apartment uncomfortably stuffy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After shaping the dough, I let it proof in the fridge for another nine hours or so. At that point, I didn’t want to wait on it any longer, so I baked it- first at 500 degrees farenheit with steam for 20 minutes, then at 425 for 22 additional minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-verdict&quot;&gt;The Verdict&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/GoldRush3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, I rely on friends and family as tasters of my bread, because once I’ve gone through the labor of making a loaf, I sometimes lose the ability to decide whether I like the finished product. This time, however, I don’t want to sure my bread. This loaf is incredible. Subtly sweet and warmly flavorful, with burst of bright ginger flavor, it’s a winner. This loaf isn’t fools’ gold, folks, it’s the real deal. I really pushed the hydration with this loaf, so the crumb could definitely be more open, but the lack of holes allows jam to stick nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of which, this loaf is delicious enjoyed with fruit preserves, butter, or on its own. I am interested in trying to whip some maple syrup to turn the bread into a dessert, but until then, I’ll still with a bare slice and a hot cup of black coffee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve made it this far, thanks for reading! I have a surprising discard recipe coming next!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/GoldRush.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://breadiquette.github.io/2020/09/25/Gold-Rush/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://breadiquette.github.io/2020/09/25/Gold-Rush/</guid>
        
        <category>Sourdough</category>
        
        <category>Bread</category>
        
        <category>Chocolate</category>
        
        <category>Vegan</category>
        
        <category>Oil Free</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
